בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף ג. Daf Gimmel.
It's the 16th day of the עומר, Omer, 16th of April,
and ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Okay, so we pick up about
15 lines down.
We're actually ahead, two dots. סורא ממסחריסי. Sura mimose chrisi. You're not
on the 16th דף daf of הוריות Horayot though. You're not on
the 16th דף daf of הוריות. Horayot. So we pick up about
15 lines down. We're actually ahead, two dots. סורא ממסחריסי. Sura mimose
chrisi. So רבינא Ravina said to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, you know,
it's a shame you weren't with us last night in the בית
מדרש. Beis Medrash. רבא Rava showed this great contradiction of these two
sources and he resolved it. So yesterday, the contradiction was that it
seems, at least, that by קדשים, Kodshim, if you שחט shecht an
animal and you don't have in mind anything specific, you don't have
in mind the right קרבן korban but you also don't have in
mind the wrong one, it's good. Whereas by גט, get, if it's
written without intention for the particular woman, even if it's written generically,
it's not good. And the resolution of that contradiction was, you know,
that סתם קדשים לשמן הם עומדים. stam Kodshim lishmon hem omdim. If
you're slaughtering a sacrifice, it's already sanctified as having its identity. The
קדושה kedusha defines it and therefore the act doesn't need specific intent
to define it as an act of slaughtering sacrifices. It's not a
question of what's in your mind but how essentially that the act
should be defined. Whereas by writing a גט, get, you're sort of
just starting with raw material. There's nothing that sort of defines this
גט, get, you know, as this particular woman's גט. get. So that
needs specific intent to be invested into it. And therefore generic intent
does not work. So that was that contradiction and that resolution. Very
important, the question about סתמא לשמן. staman lishmon. And now we do
with another contradiction and another resolution. סורא ממסחריסי. Sura mimose chrisi. רבא
Rava also showed another contradiction of two statements.
Which is the day you missed the בית מדרש.
Beis Medrash. Exactly. So you missed a lot. He missed a lot.
He missed a lot. Okay. מי אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Mi
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. Did רב יהודה Rav Yehuda really say
in the name of רב, Rav, חטאת ששחטה לשם עולה פסולה שחטה
לשם חולין כשירה. Chatat she-shachatah leshem olah pesula, shachatah leshem chulin keshera.
So here's a new teaching, which we haven't been introduced to yet,
I mean we're only on דף ג, Daf Gimmel, but it's interesting,
right? If you שחט shecht it for a wrong קרבן, korban, it's
invalid. But if you שחט shecht it for the sake of a
non-קרבן, korban, a non-קרבן, korban,
it is valid. Somehow it's like a completely irrelevant thought. It's so
off-base, it's not even like, you know, it's sort of like when
we were learning in הוריות. Horayot. If you do a פסק psak
that's against an explicit פסוק, pasuk, like you don't even get traction
if you're, you know, it's not even so. Therefore it doesn't affect
its status. By the way, we're going to see in a little
bit that there's a whole that there's a difference between whether you're
mistaken about its identity or you know its identity and you intend
something else. And for the most part we're talking about the latter,
which is a bizarre scenario just to begin with. That you know
what it is and you're still treating it as something else.
לשמו או שלא לשמו לשם חולין. Lishmo o shelo lishmo leshem chulin.
Right, right, right. Okay. Anyway well we'll see about that by the
חולין chulin actually. We'll yeah, okay. We'll worry about that. שחטה לשם
חולין כשירה. Shachatah leshem chulin keshera. It was שחט-ed shecht as חולין.
chulin. It's totally כשר. kosher. Okay. So because it's such an irrelevant
thought. So אלמא, alma, you see, דמינא מחריב בה, demina machriv ba,
one of its own kind can destroy it, דלאו
מינא, delav mina, something that's completely irrelevant to it, לא מחריב בה,
lo machriv ba, cannot destroy it. Like it's like the threat is
always the greatest by those that are closest to you. Okay. Somebody
completely, you know, distant or whatever, like you know you're not threatened
by them. Okay. So anyway, okay.
ורמינהו, Varminhu, I'll ask you on this. כל הגט שנכתב שלא לשמו
פסול. Kol haget shenichtav shelo lishmo pasul.
Back to the גט get case. If it's written not for the
sake of this woman, it's invalid. ואפילו לשם עובדי כוכבים נמי פסול.
Ve-afilu leshem ovdei kochavim nami pasul. Presumably even if it's written for
a non-Jew, for a non-Jewish woman. So a non-Jewish woman would seem
completely irrelevant to the world of גיטין, Gittin, you know, of הלכה
halachic גיטין, Gittin, the same way a חולין, chulin, a non-sanctified animal,
is irrelevant to the world of slaughtering animals. So why don't we
say that that's like just a completely irrelevant thought and it's and
it's not destructive? So the answer is obvious. This is like a
softball question based on what we said yesterday.
So the גמרא Gemara says ומשני veshani and the answer was, גט,
get, by the case of גט, get, by the way לשם עובדי
כוכבים מינה. leshem ovdei kochavim mina. Fine, let's say you didn't have
intention for that non-Jewish woman. Okay. הוי ליה סתמא. Havi leh stama.
It still the problem is you didn't have specific intention for the
right woman. It's done generically. And we just resolved yesterday וסתמא פסול.
v’stama pasul. Generic intent doesn't work by a גט. get. By a
גט get it's only כשר kosher if you have specific intent for
the right woman. So the right it's not that it's so, oh
don't you say if it's off-base it shouldn't be destructive? It's not
destructive, it's the absence of the right intent. Okay. קדשים, Kodshim, but
by קדשים, Kodshim, דלאו חולין מיניהו. delav chulin mineihu. Once you remove
the once you say it's not a negative thought because it's so
irrelevant. Okay. So you don't have a bad so you don't have
a negative thought. So הוי ליה סתמא. havi leh stama. So you
just have something that's שחט-ed shecht generically. That thought of חולין chulin
is considered so irrelevant we're not even paying attention to it. You
didn't have the right thought, you didn't have the wrong thought. Fine.
By קדשים Kodshim we said yesterday that if as long as you
don't have the wrong thought it's okay. הוי ליה סתמא וסתמא כשירה.
Havi leh stama v’stama keshera. And סתמא stama is okay. So that's
not a question because it could still be that something that's an
irrelevant thought is completely off-base. case and it's irrelevant, okay? And nevertheless
by a גט get you still have a problem because a גט
get doesn't just need the absence of a wrong thought, it needs
actually the right thought. But we're not done. The rest of today's
דף daf is going to be about this issue about is it
מינה mina or not מינה? mina? Is it of its kind or
not of its kind? So let's take a look. Okay, והתניא, ve-hatanya,
so the גמרא Gemara says...
I'm sorry, ורמינהו מילתא אחריתי, ve-raminhu milta achreiti, but then he asks
another contradiction, and this one was not so easy to answer. מי
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב חטאת ששחטה לשם עולה פסולה שחטה לשם
חולין כשרה Mi amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Chatat she-shachat-ha l'shem ola
pesula, shachat-ha l'shem chullin k'sheira that if you שחט shacht it as
an עולה ola it's invalid, if you שחט shacht it as something
as a non-sanctified animal it's כשר. kosher. אלמא דמינה מחריב בה דלא
מינה לא מחריב בה. Alma d'mina machriv bah, d'lo mina lo machriv
bah. You see that only something of its kind can be destructive,
something completely irrelevant cannot be destructive. והתניא, Ve-hatanya, now
but we have a question from a ברייתא beraita which is very,
which is basically from last week's פרשה. parsha. Okay, תוכו, tocho, it
says by a כלי חרס kli cheres by a pottery vessel, כל
אשר יפול עליו מהם אל תוכו יטמא. kol asher yipol alav meihem
el tocho yitma. Let's get the actual פסוק. pasuk. I mean,
but if I שחט shacht a קרבן korban לשם עבודה זרה, l'shem
avoda zara, we don't
say 'Oh, it's so out of the
פרשה.' parsha.
It's... Alright, that's true, that's true. Alright.
It says like this, it says,
okay, this is about the שרצים. shratzim. וכל אשר יפול עליו מהם
במותם יטמא מכל כלי עץ או בגד או עור או שק כל
כלי אשר יעשה מלאכה בהם. ve-chol asher yipol alav meihem be-motam yitma
mi-kol kli eitz o beged o or o sak, kol kli asher
yei'aseh melacha bahem. That's not the one. וכלי חרס אשר יפול מהם
אל תוכו כל אשר בתוכו יטמא ואותו תשברו. Ve-kli cheres asher yipol
meihem el tocho, kol asher be-tocho yitma ve-oto tishboru. So
here you have your כלי חרס, kli cheres, the הלכה halacha is
is that a כלי חרס kli cheres is מטמא מאוירו, metamei mei-aviro,
from its air space. Okay? So if something touches a כלי חרס
kli cheres it's not the כלי חרס kli cheres is not טמא.
tamei. Here you have a שרץ, shretz, okay, that's in the כלי
חרס, kli cheres, it's in the תוך toch of the כלי, kli,
even without touching it, it communicates its טומאה tumah to the כלי
חרס, kli cheres, so the כלי חרס kli cheres is now טמא.
tamei.
If it's dead.
If it's dead, thank you. Okay, and now you have something else
here, I don't know, some food or something like that, okay? And
it doesn't even have to be touching it, it could be suspended
in mid-air. Once you have, now it's not that the שרץ shretz
is מטמא metamei the food, the שרץ shretz is מטמא metamei the
air space... well, the כלי חרס, kli cheres, okay? And then the
כלי חרס kli cheres is מטמא metamei so even if you took
the שרץ shretz out now, really, okay, now that you have a
טמא כלי חרס, tamei kli cheres, this טמא כלי חרס tamei kli
cheres is now מטמא metamei like everything that is in it, okay?
So it's מטמא metamei the food. Alright, so that's the הלכה halacha
of that it's יפול מהם אל תוכו, yipol meihem el tocho, something
falls into it, כל אשר בתוכו. kol asher be-tocho. So it becomes
טמא tamei when the טומאה tumah is in it. Okay, that's one
תוכו. tocho. Okay? This is, this is כל אשר אשר יפול מהם
אל תוכו.
kol asher asher yipol meihem
el tocho. Okay? This is in it and it's מטמא metamei it.
And then this is
כל
אשר בתוכו יטמא.
kol asher
be-tocho yitma. Anything inside, okay? So it has to be in the
air space to be מטמא metamei the כלי, kli, and then anything
in the air space is נטמא nitma from the כלי. kli. Alright,
now we're going to see how this is relevant. Okay.
ותניא: Ve-hatanya: תוכו ולא תוך תוכו, tocho ve-lo toch tocho, not the
inside of the inside. ואפילו כלי שטף מציל. ve-afilu kli shetef matzil.
And even a כלי שטף, kli shetef, which is like a rinsing
garment vessel, meaning a non-כלי חרס, kli cheres, like metal or wood
or whatever, saves. So what does that mean? It means that if
you have, let me see if I have some other colored
here, keep on losing my markers. Hanan gave you a whole set,
right?
I know, and then I don't know what happened. Okay.
So let's say here you have,
okay,
there we go, look at that. Okay, here you have a nice
glass, you know, a glass, a drinking glass, okay? And this טומאה
tumah is... the drinking glass is inside this larger כלי חרס. kli
cheres. The mouth of it, the opening of it, is above the
mouth of the כלי חרס, kli cheres, and this is inside. So
the whole... and this food is inside.
It doesn't even have to be like stopped up.
Correct. Open the air, but it's higher than it. So then the...
what you say is this food is not considered in the כלי
חרס. kli cheres. It's considered to be in the drinking glass, okay?
So it's what is בתוכו be-tocho directly in the air space of
the כלי חרס, kli cheres, in the כלי חרס, kli cheres, not
בתוך תוכו. be-toch tocho. This is in a glass and the glass
is... now if the glass ended below the mouth of the כלי
חרס, kli cheres, that would all still be considered in.
Unless it was like stopped up, right?
Yeah, we're not going to deal with צמיד פתיל. tzamid patil. Now
if this is higher though, it is considered to be in its
own space. It's in the glass and it's not in the כלי
חרס. kli cheres. That's the הלכה. halacha.
Did you say glass because it's not חרס, cheres, if it was
another חרס?
cheres? No, certainly, certainly חרס cheres it would not be מציל. matzil.
Even, that's the הלכה. halacha. ההלכה היא ולא תוך תוך ואפילו כלי
שטף מציל. ha-halacha hi ve-lo toch toch ve-afilu kli shetef matzil.
Even not a כלי חרס kli cheres is מציל. matzil. Certainly if
it was a כלי חרס kli cheres it would be מציל matzil
because then that's the issue about מינה mina and לא מינה. lo
mina. Okay? Then you could say, well, it's in כלי kli B,
it's not in כלי kli A. But here even if it's in
something irrelevant we say that that's מציל matzil it, it saves it.
So it's not considered to be in the כלי חרס. kli cheres.
Okay, ואפילו V'afilu so anything, anything that it is, any כלי kli
B that it's in, whether it's a כלי חרס kli cheres or
not a כלי חרס kli cheres protects that and it's not נטמא.
nitma.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now why is that
a question? It's a question because why don't we just say that
if something is its own type, it's relevant. If it's a different
type, it's not relevant. So if this were a כלי חרס, kli
cheres, this blue thing, I would understand. You'll say it's in כלי
חרס kli cheres B, it's not in כלי חרס kli cheres A,
so therefore it's not נטמא. nitma. But if this is irrelevant, לאו
מינה, lav mina, so then it should, right, it should not be,
you know, it should it should not be מחרב בה, machrib ba,
but in מחרב machrib here it's a different sense because מחרב machrib
is not necessarily something bad, but it shouldn't like contradict, you know,
it shouldn't have an impact on the other thing. So if it's
a glass, well a glass is irrelevant to the world of כלי
חרס. kli cheres. So from the כלי חרס kli cheres world, it's
still in the כלי חרס, kli cheres, it's still in כלי חרס
kli cheres A. And nevertheless you don't say that. You say that
even though that this is glass, which is לאו מינה, lav mina,
not of the same genre, okay, nevertheless it has an impact on
how you look at where this food is. Okay, so that goes
against our general principle that only something should have an impact if
it's מינה, mina, if it's of the same type. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, so that's a good that's the question. ושני, V'shani,
and they answered, עשו חולין אצל קדשים כמחיצה אצל תנור. asu chullin
etzel kodshim k'mechitzah etzel tannur. Okay,
so the they the answer was the following. This is still מינה.
mina. Okay, this glass, it's still a vessel. And it's still a
vessel that's still of the same genre. So that's why it has
an impact because it's in a vessel.
What do you mean of the same genre?
Genre of the כלי חרס. kli cheres. The question was, the answer
the question was I would understand why a כלי חרס, kli cheres,
if this was if this is A,
that's vessel A and this is vessel B. And we're saying that
the food is in B, it's not in A. So it's saying
look, based on your principle, if B were כלי חרס, kli cheres,
I would understand מינה מחרב בה. mina machrib ba. The fact that
it's in something of the similar genre, כלי חרס kli cheres כלי
חרס, kli cheres, means that we it has an impact on the
outer thing. We see it in B and we don't see it
in A. Okay, but if it's B is not מינה, mina, if
it's glass, okay, then I should say לא מחרב בה, lo machrib
ba, it doesn't have an impact on this food's relationship to A,
right, within the world of כלי חרס kli cheres the glass is
irrelevant. So within the world of כלי חרס kli cheres we should
call it to be in A. That's if you call talk say
that the principle is the לאו מינה לא מחרב בה, lav mina
lo machrib ba, something not of its genre has no doesn't have
an impact on it. Okay, that was the question. And the answer
was no. B is really מינה. mina. At the end of the
day it's a vessel. Okay, you know, an עולה olah is not
the מין min of a חטאת. chattas. Right? The question is how
narrowly or broadly you define your categories. But they're still all קדשים.
kodshim. So this is also it's not a כלי חרס kli cheres
but it's still a כלי. kli. So since it's still a כלי,
kli, that's enough to have an impact the same way עולה olah
has an impact on חטאת chattas and it defines it to be
outside of A and in B. So it's like let's say a
piece of artwork would make a difference. But so that's what we're
saying. I will give you though an example of something that's really
לאו מינה lav mina that doesn't have an impact. You know what's
really לאו מינה lav mina that doesn't have an impact? If it's
not in
the
vessel B, but if it's there's a wall B here that divides
the כלי חרס kli cheres into two. Okay, and if there's a
wall that divides the כלי חרס kli cheres into two and the
thing is here, you don't say that it protects the thing over
here. Okay, and that is really a case of לא, lo, only
if it's in a different vessel do we say it's not in
the כלי חרס. kli cheres. Okay, that is מינה mina and because
it's a vessel it's a some it defines a different relationship that
this object has, it's not in the כלי חרס, kli cheres, it's
in vessel B. But if the thing is a wall, that doesn't
say oh it's only in this half, the טומאה tumah is only
in this half and not in that half.
I want you to think of קל וחומר kal v'chomer if there's
like a wall, you know.
Well that's exactly the point. So let's take a look. That's the
principle of לאו מינה לא מחרב בה. lav mina lo machrib ba.
Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so it says like this.
No, עשו, asu, so the answer is, עשו חולין אצל קדשים. asu
chullin etzel kodshim. חולין chullin is is wait what's this for ושני?
sheini? ושני, V'shani, and it answered, that was the problem, and it
answered, עשו חולין אצל קדשים, asu chullin etzel kodshim, חולין chullin vis-a-vis
קדשים kodshim is a significant לאו מינה. lav mina. It's completely out
of the category. So the analogy is not to a glass vessel.
The analogy is כמחיצה אצל תנור. k'mechitzah etzel tannur. If you had
a wall going down the middle of a תנור, tannur, they would
have a חרס תנור, cheres tannur, an oven made out of pottery,
and the oven though is still considered to be a כלי. kli.
There a wall is irrelevant to a כלי. kli. Okay, and that's
the better comparison. כלי, kli, whether it's glass or חרס, cheres, that's
still like עולה olah versus חטאת. chattas. So that's why it has
an impact. A wall, that's like חולין, chullin, that's real a different
category and that doesn't have an impact. Okay,
so מה מחיצה אצל תנור לא מהניא לה כלל, ma mechitzah etzel
tannur lo mehanya lah klal, the same way a wall down the
middle of a of a תנור tannur does not have an impact,
which
אף חולין אצל קדשים לא מהניא לכלל. af chullin etzel kodshim lo
mehanya l'klal. The same is true by חולין chullin vis-a-vis קדשים. kodshim.
Okay. So דתנן, detnan, we're going to, can we explain the case,
let's explain the case
first, דתנן: detnan: תנור שחצצו בנסרים. tannur shechatzatzo b'nesarim. You have an
oven, okay, imagine that this now isn't a כלי, kli, it's an
oven, but halachically it's still a כלי, kli, okay, you know, they
would just have like a fire on the bottom or whatever, it
doesn't matter. It's a, this is your oven now, okay. Okay. And
it's made out of חרס. cheres. And you basically used planks to
divide it, to divide it in the middle. You don't make a
wall out of חרס cheres that actually might define it as a
separate oven, okay, but you use planks, או ביריות, o biyriyot, or
you have a little, you know, curtain. I don't know how long
a curtain's going to last in an oven, but for the temporary,
you know, it's a defunct oven, it doesn't matter. ונמצא שרץ במקום
אחד, v'nimtza sheretz b'makom echad, and you have a שרץ sheretz over
here. הכל טמא, hakol tamei, everything anywhere in the oven is טמא.
tamei. We don't say it's not תוכו. tocho. It is תוכו. tocho.
A wall doesn't define it as being in a different airspace. Only
a different כלי kli does. A wall is irrelevant to the world
of כלים. keilim. Okay,
הכל טמא. hakol tamei. כוורת שהיא פחותה ופקוקה בקש. keiveret shehi p'chuta
u'p'kuka b'kash. A כוורת, keiveret, anybody who has learned כלים, keilim, כוורת
keiveret is like a the whole big, whatever, it's like a classic
case. Anyway, כוורת keiveret literally means a beehive. It's some type of
a vessel that's basically shaped like a beehive. Imagine it as some
cylindrical vessel, okay, but it is פחותה, p'chuta, it has opened up.
There's a big hole in the vessel. So halachically it stops being
a vessel. And then you go ahead and you stuff up that
hole with straw, which is not a permanent fix. So you have
something which is shaped like a vessel, this would be your כוורת,
keiveret, okay, but halachically it's not a vessel, because it had a
big hole in it and then you filled up the hole. So
anyway, halachically this really only functions as a מחיצה. mechitza. It does
not have a status as a vessel.
So it's just like a colander, right?
Yeah, like a like whatever, I don't know, a colander,
but it's full of holes.
Yeah, yeah, but it depends on the size of the hole. But
anyway, I don't want to deal with that right now. Okay, anyway,
okay, so it it is a vessel, looks like a vessel, like
it has an inside and a container, but halachically it's not, because
it had a big hole that was just stopped up temporarily. Okay,
so effectively it functions here as a wall and not as a
vessel. So that case, when again we're dealing with walls and not
with vessels,
ומשולשלת לאויר התנור, u'meshulshelet l'avir hatannur, and it's lowered down and suspended
in the airspace of the oven, שרץ בתוכה התנור טמא. sheretz betochah
hatannur tamei. If a שרץ sheretz is inside this כוורת, keiveret, this
beehive as it were, then it's not like it's in a separate
vessel, because halachically it's not a vessel, and everything in the oven
is טמא. tamei. שרץ בתנור אוכלים
שבתוכה טמאים. sheretz batannur ochalin shebetochah tme'im. If the שרץ sheretz is
in the
תנור, tannur, the food inside of it is טמא. tamei. Okay, so
basically, bottom line is it's an it's a stranger case, the כוורת,
keiveret, but halachically it's like a מחיצה. mechitza. When is something saved
in a כלי חרס? kli cheres? If it's in a real vessel
inside of the כלי חרס, kli cheres, that is מינה, minah, even
if it's not a חרס cheres vessel. But if it's only on
if it's something that's technically not a vessel, even though it is
actually in its own airspace in a physical sense, since halachically this
isn't a vessel, it's only defined as a wall, it does not
divide, it does not make it defined as in a different space.
So actually this fits very nicely with our pattern, with our sort
of structure, you know, that דלא מינה לא מחריב בה, d'la minah
lo machriv bah, one minute, okay,
okay, ורבי אליעזר מטהר, v'Rabbi Eliezer metaher, and Rabbi Eliezer says no,
I'm sorry, it's טהור. tahor. Okay, I'm not I'm sorry, whatever, the
אוכלים ochalin is טהור. tahor. Now רש"י Rashi says he would say
that even if it was a straight wall, he would say the
food is טהור. tahor. תוספות Tosafot says that he would say that
only in the case of the כוורת, keiveret, only in the case
of the beehive, because it's a quasi-vessel. Okay, I don't want to
actually worry about that right now, but anyway, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
actually does say no, this actually is just as good as being
in a different vessel, on the other side of a wall actually
does work to save it. Okay.
But which is a bigger question, I'm just not understanding something about...
Okay, what's your question?
My bigger question is I thought חולין שנשחטו בעזרה chullin shenishchetu ba'azarah
is its own separate פסול.
psul. חולין שנשחטו, chullin shenishchetu, yeah.
So if there's a חטאת ששחטה לשם חולין, chattas sheshachatah l'shem chullin,
then it becomes חולין שנשחטו בעזרה, chullin shenishchetu ba'azarah, no? Isn't that
its own problem?
No, no, no, only if the animal is חולין. chullin. Okay, anyway,
so...
But what if I brought in my own...
Okay, so okay, אמר רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer, now רבי אליעזר
מטהר. Rabbi Eliezer metaher. אמר רבי אליעזר, amar Rabbi Eliezer, קל וחומר,
kal v'chomer, I will argue to you that this thing is טהור
tahor from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Okay, let's just read it
like רש"י, Rashi, which is let's just assume he's arguing even on
the case of a straight wall. He says that's considered a different
space and it's טהור. tahor. Here's my קל וחומר: kal v'chomer: אם
הציל בטומאת המת החמורה, im hitzil b'tumat hameis hachamura, a wall will
save something from טומאת מת. tumat meis. Here you are, you've got
your house, okay, you know, you've got your living room and your
dining room, okay, and there's a wall between them, or I don't
know, you have a subdivided house or whatever, okay, and you have
a dead body here, okay, okay, so the טומאה tumah fills up
this entire area, all right, but because there's a wall here, I
mean, maybe dining room is not a good example, because you tend
to think that there's like an opening, but let's imagine there's a
door,
okay, whatever, literally... Because there's a wall here, everybody in here is
totally טהור. tahor. So a wall is so strong that it even
prevents טומאת מת tumas meis which is the strongest טומאה tumah from
spreading. Okay, because it defines this as a different space. So how
can you tell me a wall won't save you inside of an
oven with just a dead שרץ? sheretz? Okay, walls do save. Alright,
that's his answer. Okay, so walls save lives. Okay, anyway, or save
טומאות. tumas. Anyway,
רבי אליעזר מטהר. Rebbi Eliezer mi-ta-her. רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. If it saves in a case of a weighty case
of a dead body, לא תציל בכלי חרס הקל? lo tatzil bikli
cheres hakal? Shouldn't it save inside a pottery vessel which is much
more lenient? אמרו לו: לא. Amru lo: lo. No.
אין, הציל במת חמור שכן חלוקה באהלים. In, hitzil be-meis chamur sheken
chalukah be-ohelin. By מת meis conceptually, the difference is, I mean, I'll
tell you the way רש"י Rashi reads the words and I'll sort
of nuance it a little. רש"י Rashi says in אוהל, ohel, in
homes, right, which is what an אוהל ohel is, it's like buildings,
you know, whatever, houses, conceptually, the normal way you define different types
of houses is by walls. Walls are used to divide, you know,
semi-detached houses, they're different houses, and so on, or different rooms or
whatever it is, so that's a natural thing that's used to divide
the spaces, so that's why it defines this as a different space.
תציל בכלי חרס הקל שאין חלוקין באהלים? Tatzil bikli cheres hakal she'ein
chalukin be-ohelin? By כלי חרס, kli cheres, a
כלי חרס kli cheres is a vessel. You don't divide vessels with
a wall. You could say is it in the inner vessel, the
outer vessel. So a different vessel would define a different air space.
But a wall is not a natural thing to define two separate
vessels, to split a vessel in half and to call it two
separate vessels in a different air space. So therefore, basically, the way
רש"י Rashi reads it is דלאו מיניה לא מחריב ביה. dilav minah
lo machrev beih. Okay? It's not of the same מין. min. It's
irrelevant. Walls are irrelevant to vessels, and therefore they do not make
a difference. Okay? So
the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, it's very consistent with the idea that
something that's irrelevant does not make a difference, even if in other
places it's even if it's so powerful in another place, here it's
irrelevant and it doesn't make a difference. The problem is that within
רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, right, we you know, he seems to go
against our principle. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: התינח לרבנן, hatenach l'rabbanan, this works for
the Rabbis, לרבי אליעזר מאי איכא למימר? le'Rebbi Eliezer mai ika lemeimar?
But what about רבי אליעזר? Rebbi Eliezer? He seems to reject this
idea that something irrelevant can't make a difference. He feels that even
though it's conceptually irrelevant, it does make a difference. So the גמרא
Gemara says, רבי אליעזר קל וחומר קאמר. Rebbi Eliezer kal v'chomer ka'amar.
Look, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer in general agrees to our principle that
something irrelevant doesn't have an impact. He's just making a קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. If it works by מת, meis, it should work here
even though I understand that here it's not מיניה, minah, here it's
of a different type, but nevertheless it should be based on קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but at least
he's willing to use a קל וחומר kal v'chomer logic, you know,
to override.
So therefore why doesn't he always use the קל וחומר kal v'chomer
logic? So he says,
אי הכי, ee hachi, התם נמי hatam nami or הכא נמי, hacha
nami, לימא קל וחומר? leima kal v'chomer? קדשים מחללין קדשים, חולין לא
כל שכן? Kodshim mechallelin kodshim, chullin lo kol sheken? So fine, it
doesn't matter if you start with the idea that if it's irrelevant
it shouldn't have an impact. At the end of the day, use
your קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Okay, חולין chullin I get it, it's
irrelevant, it shouldn't have an impact. But קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, if
קדשים kodshim can invalidate, certainly חולין chullin should invalidate. Okay, so we
still have a problem within רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. At the end
of the day, because רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer uses a קל וחומר,
kal v'chomer, it basically says that something that's irrelevant should make a
difference. Okay, so אלא ella fine, you're right. According to רבי אליעזר,
Rebbi Eliezer, you have to say that it's not based on this
principle. This principle,
the חכמים Chachamim are probably committed to this principle, but רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer is not. But still, the reason קדשים kodshim would be
different would be based on a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, normally something that's
irrelevant based on a קל וחומר kal v'chomer could have an impact,
but not here by
קדשים. kodshim.
אלא טעמא דרב כרבי אלעזר. Ella, ta'ama d'Rav ke'Rebbi Elazar. The reason
רב Rav says, not now this is not it's confusing, it's not
רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, it's רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar the אמורא. Amora.
Some actually have the גירסא girsa רב עילאי Rav Ilai which makes
it easier. Fine, רב's Rav reason that חולין chullin doesn't have an
impact, at least to explain it according to רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
is based on a different reason. דאמר רבי אלעזר De'amar Rebbi Elazar
or רבי עילאי, Rebbi Ilai, מאי טעמא דרב? mai ta'ama d'Rav? What
is the reason? You see it's an אמורא, Amora, he's explaining רב.
Rav. What's the reason of רב? Rav? Because it says by תרומה,
terumah, ולא יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל את אשר ירימו לה'. v'lo
yechalelu es kodshei b'nei Yisrael es asher yarimu l'Hashem. So the simple
meaning of this verse is it's a command: they shall not defile
the sanctified things of Israel. But we're reading it as, you know,
that unsanctified things shall not have the ability to be מחלל את
קדשי בני ישראל. mechallel es kodshei b'nei Yisrael. They will not be
able to. If it's חולין, chullin, חולין chullin cannot be
מחלל קדשי בני ישראל. mechallel kodshei b'nei Yisrael. קדשים מחללין קדשים. Kodshim
mechallelin kodshim. Sanctified things
are, you know, defile. So basically bottom line is it's like this.
One way to explain it is a general principle, something irrelevant doesn't
have an impact and that works for the rabbis by כלי חרס
kli cheres as well, that walls don't have an impact, but it
doesn't work for רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, in principle, maybe it should have an impact, but a פסוק
pasuk tells you it doesn't. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
אמר אתא קרא אפקיה מקל וחומר. amar ata kra afkei mikal vachomer.
So the פסוק pasuk is coming and it's saying don't use your
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, this פסוק pasuk is telling you that at
least by קדשים, kodshim, a thought about non-sanctified animals doesn't impact it.
So if that's true, back to our case by the כלי חרס.
kli cheres. Let's say the same thing. הכא נמי לכתוב תוכו ליפקה
מקל וחומר. hacha nami lichtov tocho lipkei mikal vachomer.
The פסוק pasuk says תוכו tocho כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. kol asher
betocho yitma.
So why don't we use the extra word תוכו? tocho? This sort
of assumes that even had it not said it, I would have
obviously somehow inferred that something had to be on the inside. Or
רש"י Rashi says it could have said תוך, toch, it has to
say תוכו, tocho, and the גמרא Gemara will say that later. So
the extra verse of תוכו tocho maybe should tell me yes, a
מחיצה mechitzah based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer should protect it.
But the word תוכו tocho is telling you that it has to
really be defined as, you know, as not on the inside of
the thing. And therefore only something in a different vessel is really
defined as not being on the inside. So why don't we just
use that extra word תוכו tocho to limit this idea to say
that the מחיצה, mechitzah, right, because now what do we have? We
have that for the חכמים chachamim if it's irrelevant like a wall
or חולין chullin it doesn't make a difference. For רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, even though he might in principle say it shouldn't make a
difference, he'll use a קל וחומר kal vachomer to say it does.
Okay, but then a פסוק pasuk can say no, no, no, at
the end of the day it is irrelevant, don't use it. And
that's what it says by קדשים. kodshim. At the end of the
day, the פסוק pasuk says ולא יחללו, velo yechallelu, you know, חולין
chullin is an irrelevant thought, don't use it, don't use a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, it won't make a difference. So why don't
we say the same thing here? A wall is fundamentally irrelevant, okay,
and תוכו tocho should tell you even though by a קל וחומר
kal vachomer you say we should, it should make a difference, תוכו
tocho should tell you it doesn't make a difference. Why not say
the same thing? So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי לכתוב תוכו
ליפקה מקל וחומר. hacha nami lichtov tocho lipkei mikal vachomer. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, the word תוכו tocho is already used up.
האי תוכו מיבעי ליה לאוכלים שגיבבם בטיט והכניסן לאויר תנור. hai tocho
mibaye leh le'ochlim shegibevam betit vehichnisan l'avir tanur. So here's another scenario.
You have food and you wrapped them all in plaster. You have
it stored in plaster. Hopefully you'll be able to crack open the
plaster and the food will still be edible. Maybe it's inside plastic
and then the plaster, and the whole thing is inside plastic and
you put that food here, which is, you know, imagine this black
thing I just did is a plastic thing that's around it. So
the question is is the food טמא? tamei? It's inside the כלי
חרס, kli cheres, okay, but it's not even, but it's not inside
a different vessel, you know, so you can't say it's not תוכו.
tocho. It's not even on the other side of a wall, so
it's a different air space. It's totally within. It's just that it
has a wrapper around it. Okay, and that is טמא. tamei. Okay,
now why would I have thought otherwise?
Okay, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salcka daitach amina, I would have thought הואיל
ובנגיעה לא מטמא, ho'il uvenegi'ah lo metamei, since this food is protected
from becoming טמא tamei through touch, so therefore
באוירא נמי לא מטמו, be'avira nami lo metamu, can't also become טמא
tamei through the air space. Maybe air space operates as a type
of a touch, and if it can't be touched, it's not טמא.
tamei. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that it is טמא. tamei. So what
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say is I'm not going to use
the word תוכו tocho to tell me that a מחיצה mechitzah does
not save, I will say a מחיצה mechitzah does save. I will
use the word תוכו tocho not to limit, but to expand. I
will use the word תוכו tocho just to say even this food
that's wrapped up in this plaster, at the end of the day
that is still תוכו tocho and that is still טמא. tamei. Okay.
ורבנן verabbanan and the rabbis would say back כאן לא צריכי קרא,
kan lo tzerichi kra, that's so obvious, of course that's טמא. tamei.
It's still תוכו. tocho. You don't need a פסוק pasuk to tell
you that. Okay, so therefore there's no reason I would think just
because it's wrapped in plaster, you know, כלי חרס kli cheres does
not work, it works through air space, it doesn't work through touch,
so of course that's טמא. tamei. You don't need a פסוק. pasuk.
So what do we have at the end of the day? Let
me just sum this up. We have at the end of the
day the following. The rabbis say if it's irrelevant it doesn't matter.
And that's why a thought about חולין chullin doesn't matter, and that's
why a wall in a כלי חרס kli cheres doesn't matter. Walls
are powerful, but they're not powerful by כלי חרס, kli cheres, they're
irrelevant. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says maybe I agree to that in
principle, but based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer I'll say it
will matter. And that's why walls do matter in a כלי חרס.
kli cheres. So why, okay, so then why don't they matter by,
why doesn't חולין chullin matter by קדשים? kodshim? Oh, I got a
פסוק. pasuk. פסוק Pasuk tells me don't, חולין chullin doesn't matter. Use
a פסוק pasuk by כלי חרס, kli cheres, use a word תוכו
tocho to tell you walls don't matter. And the answer at the
end of the day is yeah, but I need that to tell
me some other הלכה. halacha. Okay, and therefore because I don't have
a פסוק pasuk to stop it from mattering, even though walls are
irrelevant, based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer they do matter by
כלי חרס. kli cheres. Yes, question.
Yeah, going back when we... didn't discuss it, but didn't we say
if this vessel inside a vessel had a stopper on it, then
the food— That's צמיד פתיל, tzamid patil, that's more by אהל המת
ohel hamet and I really don't want to discuss it, okay?
But I'm asking that because like why isn't the wrapping also like
a self-contained— Yeah,
but that's you know yeah but let's not go there okay? I
mean it's whatever it's just way too— yeah right. That's when it's
inside a vessel at the end of the day. Just being wrapped
is not that's the whole point. It has to be about being
in a different space. It's not being— so that's exactly yeah being
in a vessel covered by a seal, a צמיד פתיל, tzamid patil,
is better than being wrapped into this thing. That's exactly part of
the point. Okay.
So now, so that's how we resolved it. But that's this idea
that sometimes something that's less relevant, that's you know, that's is is
has less of an impact, okay, even though it should seem like
more destructive, it's completely opposed but it's just less relevant. Okay, now,
רב יוסף בר אמי רמי: שינוי קודש ה שינוי בעלים מי משני.
Rav Yosef bar Ami rami: shinnui kodesh ha shinnui be'alim mi meshani.
So now we're dealing he he wants to show another seeming contradiction.
Changing שינוי קודש, shinnui kodesh, changing the sense of you שחט shachat
a חטאת chatat and you think it's an עולה, olah, and שינוי
בעלים, shinnui be'alim, you שחט shachat something for you think it's a
חטאת chatat of ראובן Reuven and you שחט shachat it as a
חטאת chatat of שמעון. Shimon. So the basic הלכה halacha is the
following: the same way שינוי קודש shinnui kodesh has basically by you
know
by non-חטאת chatat means the animal is still כשר kasher but it
doesn't count for the owner. So if I take David's עולה olah
and I שחט shachat it as David's חטאת chatat or as David's
שלמים, shlamim, it's still a כשר עולה, kasher olah, it just doesn't
count for David. If I take David's עולה olah and I שחט
shachat it as Gloria's עולה, olah, that's שינוי בעלים, shinnui be'alim, it's
a כשר kasher animal but it doesn't count for David. Okay, so
it follows the exact same rule if I שחט shachat it for
the wrong person as if I שחט shachat it as the wrong
קרבן. korban. Now let's say it's David's חטאת, chatat, okay,
and I שחט shachat David's חטאת chatat as Gloria's חטאת, chatat, okay,
so that should mean what's the הלכה halacha by a חטאת chatat
if you make a change, what's the הלכה? halacha?
It has to be for the specific person.
Right, so a חטאת chatat if you make a change, if I
שחט shachat David's חטאת chatat as David's עולה, olah, it would be
invalid, right, פסול pasul by חטאת, chatat, right? It's not just it
doesn't count for David, it's completely invalid. So if I שחט shachat
David's חטאת chatat as Gloria's חטאת, chatat, it should also be invalid,
right? Completely invalid. So now let's see what the הלכה halacha is.
We're going to compare a change in קודש kodesh to a change
in owners, okay? So רב יוסף בר אמי רמי: שינוי קודש אשינוי
קודש ומשני. Rav Yosef bar Ami rami: shinnui kodesh a-shinnui kodesh u-meshani.
מי אמר רב: חטאת ששחטה לשם חטאת כשרה, לשם עולה פסולה. Mi
amar Rav: chatat she-shachtah l'shem chatat kesherah, l'shem olah pesulah. So רב
Rav says when you שחט shachat a חטאת chatat as an עולה
olah it's invalid, okay, אלמא alma so and he contrasted that... sorry,
חטאת ששחטה לשם חטאת כשרה,
לשם עולה פסולה.
chatat she-shachtah l'shem
chatat kesherah, l'shem olah pesulah. So if you שחט shachat a חטאת
chatat for a חטאת, chatat, hold on let me just check up
רש"י Rashi just make sure I'm saying this right.
Right, okay. So let's say, okay, this now we're going to completely
get it complicated in another way. David had to bring a חטאת
chatat for eating חלב. chelev. But when I שחט shachat it, I
had in mind that it was David's חטאת chatat for eating דם,
dam, for a different sacrifice, for a different sin, okay?
חטאת ששחטה לשם חטאת כשרה. chatat she-shachtah l'shem chatat kesherah. לשם עולה
L'shem olah but if I שחט shachat and I think it's an
עולה, olah, פסולה. pesulah. אלמא alma so this seems to tell you
the opposite of what we said before, דלאו מינה מחריב בה דמינה
לא מחריב בה. d'lav minah machriv bah d'minah lo machriv bah. The
closer something is, the less of a problem it is, okay? So
here we got a case, we got David's
חטאת chatat for דם, dam, okay? So if the change I made
is instead of דם dam I said חלב, chelev, okay, I made
that change, the הלכה halacha is כשרה. kesherah. That's not a big
deal.
But it doesn't it doesn't fulfill his obligation, does it? It may...
yes, it does. You don't have a חטאת chatat that doesn't fulfill
an obligation.
But doesn't it have to be for the specific sin?
So
it has to be sort of sanctified for the sin or whatever,
but the point is even if you have in mind the wrong
thing it still works. Right, so that's the big חידוש, chiddush, okay?
Now if I do David's חטאת chatat
לשם עולה, l'shem olah, if that's the change I make, it's invalid,
okay?
Yeah? Now if I do David's thing and I do it for
Gloria, we're going to find out what the הלכה halacha is about
that. Okay, but here, okay, here it is the case of מינה,
minah, it's similar, and here it's לאו מינה, lav minah, it's not
similar. And it's more כשר kasher when you stay right within a
similar genre, חטאת חטאת—I chatat chatat mean דם dam and חלב chelev
is not מינה minah but it's חטאת חטאת—than chatat chatat when you
make a more radical stay, right, because this is you know here
you're still basically it's still חטאת חלב chatat chelev and this is
חטאת דם, chatat dam, right? So there... it's more כשר kosher than
when you make a more radical change. That's opposite of what we
said before. Okay. So let's take a look. Okay.
שחטה לשמה ושחטה לשם חטאת כשרה לשם עולה פסולה.
Shechatah lishmah u'shechatah l'shem
chatas kesherah l'shem olah pesulah. אלמא דלאו מינה מחריב בה, Alma delav
minah machriv bah, the more something is different the more destructive it
is. דמינה לא מחריב בה. Deminah lo machriv bah. But how could
that be? ואמר רב, Ve'amar Rav, חטאת ששחטה מי שמחויב חטאת פסולה
על מי שמחויב עולה כשרה. Chatas she'shechata mi she'mechuyav Chatas pesulah al
mi she'mechuyav Olah kesherah. So let's say I דוד Dovid slaughtered it
for Gloria. So now it breaks up to two possibilities. Okay. Well,
here I guess we'll have two people. Okay. We'll have Gloria and
we'll have דוב. Dov. Okay. So here דוב Dov is חייב חטאת
chayav chatas for eating חמץ בפסח chametz b'Pesach or something. Gloria is
not חייב חטאת, chayav chatas, she's only חייב chayav an עולה olah
or whatever. She decided to be a צדקת tzadeket and she's just
donating an עולה olah to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay. So,
יישר כח Yasher koach Gloria. So, okay. So what does he say?
He says if he does it for, and if he's thinking that
it should be Gloria's, it's actually, okay, let's draw a line here
just so you see the difference of the cases, this is שינוי
בעלים shinui be'alim and this is שינוי קודש. shinui kodesh. Okay. So
if he does it for Gloria, so she's חייב chayav an עולה,
olah, that's like an irrelevant thought that the כהן Kohen is thinking
about Gloria because
Gloria isn't even in the same category as a חייב חטאת. chayav
chatas. That's not really changing the owner. It's so off base, it's
not in the world of חטאת Chatas Gloria, that it's actually okay.
Whereas דוב, Dov, it is in the world of חטאת Chatas and
it's a wrong owner, so it's not good. Okay. So here you
have the opposite, right? If something is more off base, it's, which
is מינה, minah, it's כשר, kosher, and if it's more in the
same category, it's more of a meaningful change. I'm sorry, this is
לאו מינה. lav minah. If it's more off base, it's כשר, kosher,
and if it's more in the same category and more relevant, it's
פסול. pasul.
Do you see that? Okay, so here this fits with our previous
idea. If you go completely to a different world, to a world
of non-חטאת, non-Chatas, you're actually safe. Within the world of חטאת, Chatas,
when you change it, you're no good. Okay. That fits with our
previous thing: the more you're in the same world, the more destructive
it is. But here it doesn't work that way. Here you stay
within the פרשה parsha and you're actually okay. All right.
When you say it's okay and you've got the two different owners,
it's okay for which of them?
No, it's always דוד'ס Dovid's קרבן. korban. It only works for דוד.
Dovid. You can't make it somebody else's קרבן korban when the כהן
Kohen is thinking about Gloria when he's שחטינג shechting דוד, Dovid,
then
we're saying דוד'ס Dovid's it still works, it's דוד'ס Dovid's קרבן. korban.
That thought was like he was thinking about, you know, the ballgame.
It's completely irrelevant. Okay. It's like he's thinking about he has to
pick up his kids after this day in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. All right. So it doesn't change it. It actually means it's
an irrelevant thought and it works when it works, it works like
it should have worked. Okay. So here if it's off base, it's
okay. If it's within the פרשה, parsha, it's more destructive. That's consistent
to what we said before, right? But here when you're within the
פרשה, parsha, you're actually completely okay. Okay, so let's see what the
answer is. The question is how big, you know, what פרשה parsha
are we talking about? Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay. דמינה לא מחריב בה והאמר רב חטאת ששחטה על מי שמחויב
חטאת פסולה על מי שמחויב עולה כשרה. Deminah lo machriv bah ve'amar
Rav Chatas she'shechata al mi she'mechuyav Chatas pesulah al mi she'mechuyav Olah
kesherah. אלמא דבר מינה מחריב בה, Alma debar minah machriv bah, something
of the same category is destructive. דלאו מינה לא מחריב בה, Delav
minah lo machriv bah, if it's not of the same category, it's
not destructive. ומשני, U'meshani, and the answer was, התם ושחט אותה לחטאת
אמר רחמנא. Hasam v'shachat osah l'chatas amar Rachmana. ברוך אתה ה' אלהינו
מלך העולם שהכל נהיה בדברו.
Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech HaOlam shehakol
nihiyah bidvaro. סמכיה כוחיה וסמא ליה עלמא. Samchei kocha v'sama lei alma.
Okay.
So there it says you should שחט shecht it for a חטאת,
Chatas, everything was done right. Okay. This sort of goes to דוד'ס
Dovid's question. Is it a חטאת Chatas of דם? dam? Yes. But
when the תורה Torah demands what thoughts you have, what are the
פסוקים pesukim then when the תורה Torah says what you have to
have in mind? Okay. It says ושחט אותה לחטאת. v'shachat osah l'chatas.
It doesn't say you have to have in mind the right type
of חטאת, Chatas, just that you have in mind a חטאת. Chatas.
So the actual point here is the reason it's okay is really
what I would call an issue of precision. How precise does the
תורה Torah demand that you be? Okay. It's not like oh, it's
a bad thought but because it's because it's in the same פרשה,
parsha, it's not a problem. No. Same פרשה parsha is actually more
of a problem. The reason, right, like we see in all the
other cases, the closer something is the more of a problem. The
reason this is okay is because the תורה Torah doesn't demand this
degree of precision. The תורה Torah just says you only have to
have in mind that it's a חטאת. Chatas. You don't have to
have in mind what type of a חטאת Chatas this is. So
this is, this is, this is like below the level of precision
that the תורה Torah demands. And that's why that's okay, okay? Whereas,
it has to be the same person, right? Whereas,
the person we're going to get to, הכא וכיפר עליו, hacha vechiper
alav, וכיפר עליו. vechiper alav.
So this is telling you you have to have in mind the
right person, okay? And you don't have in mind the right person.
Now, that's why if it's totally off base, it's irrelevant, we throw
it out, right? The more something is distant, the more irrelevant it
is. But if it's within the world of the חטאת Chatas because
he's thinking about Dov rather than thinking about David, okay,
then you have violated וכיפר עליו. vechiper alav. You are not intending
the right person. This is a completely irrelevant thought, this is thinking
about picking up the kids. This is a problem of וכיפר עליו.
vechiper alav. Okay, so the reason this is no good is because
you know,
this is no good is because it violates having in mind the
right person. And this is an irrelevant thought. The reason this is
good is because there's no demand that you have in mind the
right type of sin. All you have to have in mind is
חטאת Chatas and you did have in mind חטאת, Chatas, okay, as
opposed to חטאת Chatas and עולה, Olah, you actually switched this. All
right?
Is this how we follow,
or did we just discuss that? Yeah, I'm pretty sure, I'd have
to look up, I mean... okay, so, all right, so, now, so
we're almost done. Okay, הכא וכיפר עליו חבירו דומיא דידיה hacha vechiper
alav chavero dumya didei and on him it has to be his,
not his friend, for you have to have in mind the
right owner. The friend has to be somewhat in the same category
as the guy you're supposed to be
intending, שמחוייב כפרה כמוהו, shemechuyav kapara kamohu, that he is similarly obligated
and therefore having in mind Gloria who's not even obligated in a
חטאת Chatas is an irrelevant thought. Okay, so the reason this is
good, we're still staying with our principle: the closer something is, the
more relevant the thought, the more destructive the
thought. The reason this is good is just that the תורה Torah
does not demand that degree of precision. All right? All right, now
we go on. Okay. Now, last one. רב חביבא
רמי שינוי בעלים אתוך תוכו ומשני. Rav Chaviva rami shinui be'alim atoch
tocho umshani. He's got a question about changing the owner and comparing
that to a question about תוך תוכו toch tocho and let's see
what his answer is. Okay, back to
the תוך תוכו toch tocho of the כלי חרס, kli cheres, we
thought we were free from that. Okay. ומי אמר רב חטאת ששחטה
משם מחוייב חטאת פסולה משם מחוייב עולה כשירה? umi amar Rav Chatas
sheshachata mishum mechuyav Chatas pesula mishum mechuyav Olah ksheira? Okay, here again,
it's this same idea. This seems to be consistent with our idea,
okay? When he slaughtered it for Gloria, it's כשר kosher because it's
irrelevant, it's לאו מינו. lav mino. When he slaughters it for me,
it's פסול pasul because it's מיניה. minei. Does רב Rav really say
that? אלמא דמינא מקרב ביה, alma deminei mekarav bei, if
something's of the same type, it's destructive. דלאו מינא לא מקרב ביה,
delav minei lo mekarav bei, if it's not of the same type,
it's not destructive. והתניא vehatanya תוכו ולא תוך תוכו אפילו כלי שטף
מציל. tocho velo toch tocho afilu kli shetef matzil.
We're back to this. Okay, here you see that even something that
is a different vessel can protect it, even though it's לאו מיניה,
lav minei, it still can protect it. Okay, now, remember, here תוספות
Tosafos makes this following point which is an excellent point. The גמרא's
Gemara answer to this before was, no, a different vessel is still
מיניה, minei, it's still the world of vessels. It's not like it's
a wall. It's still the world of vessels and that's why it
has an impact. Okay, that was when the גמרא Gemara was saying
it's sort of like the same way חטאת Chatas and עולה, Olah,
they're the same world. It's חולין Chulin is a different world, a
wall is a different world, but vessel and vessel are the same
world. That was the גמרא's Gemara answer before, you remember? Here though,
תוספות Tosafos points out the גמרא Gemara can't say that answer because
here the difference between Dov and Gloria is not a difference between
חולין Chulin and קדשים, Kodashim, right? It's a difference between a חטאת
Chatas and an עולה. Olah. You with me? So this is not
like, here the לאו מיניה lav minei is, it is קדשים, Kodashim,
it's just a little difference, it's an עולה, Olah, okay? And nevertheless,
that's considered to be enough irrelevant that it doesn't have an impact.
Well, the difference between Dov and Gloria here is no different than
the difference between a pottery vessel and a glass vessel, okay? So
here, why is it that thinking about Gloria, which is considered to
be so off base that it doesn't have an impact, well, a
glass vessel should also be considered so different it doesn't have an
impact. All right, that's the question. Did I lose everybody? You got
me? More or less? Yes, I lost you or yes, I didn't
lose you? Okay. The bottom line is here, here we have the
difference that מיניה minei makes a difference. Okay, I'm sorry, only something
of the same type makes a difference, of a different type does
not make a difference. So going back to the same question, if
that's true, if a different type doesn't make a difference, why does
a glass vessel make a difference? Same question that we had before.
What I was just trying to say is the same answer isn't
available because here we're still within roughly the same פרשה Parsha and
we still make this difference between same type and different type. So
let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. והתניא Vehatanya טבלו tevelu
אפילו כלי שטף מציל afilu k'li shetef matzil ומשני u'mishani ארבע arba
תוכו tocho כתיבי. kesivei. It
says תוכו tocho four times. אשר בתוכה, asher betochoh, you know it
says אשר יפול מהם אל תוכו asher yipol mehem el tocho and
אשר אל תוכו. asher el tocho. So it says תוכו tocho that
counts as four times because תוך toch is once and תוכו tocho
is two. And so it says תוכו tocho twice that gives you
four. תוך תוכו תוך תוכו. toch tocho toch tocho. חד לגופיה, chad
legufei,
once to tell you the הלכה halacha that it only causes טומאה
tumah when it's on the inside, וחד לגזירה שוה, vechad legezeira shava,
another
is a גזירה שוה gezeira shava that it's
that not only is the food טמא tamei but the vessel is
also טמא. tamei. חד תוכו של זה ולא תוכו של אחר chad
tocho shel zeh velo tocho shel acher and the other one is
to tell you that you know if it's inside of the glass
vessel here that it's saved. Okay. ואידך ve'idach תוכו ולא תוך תוכו
ואפילו כלי שטף מציל tocho velo toch tocho va'afilu k'li shetef matzil
and the final one anyway there's an extra word that tells you
that even if it's a glass vessel even though we should say
that maybe the glass vessel is considered to be something that's לאו
מיניה lav mineih not of an impact, bottom line the answer is
the extra what seems to be an extra word of תוכו tocho
tells you that even something that's a little bit irrelevant like a
glass vessel it's not a pottery vessel even that still matters here.
Okay. And that's why here it saves even though it's a little
bit off it's a little not of the same genre whereas here
because Gloria is not of the same genre as חטאת, chatas, it's
that חטאת chatas is not destructive. All right. So bottom line is
without worrying too much about the פסוקים pesukim about the תוכו tocho
the גמרא Gemara still seems that it basically likes this general way
of thinking that the closer something is the more destructive it is.
Okay. And nevertheless okay this is not a problem because that's not
a degree of precision that you need but because the closer something
is the more destructive it is, okay, therefore thinking about Dov who's
חייב חטאת chayav chatas does invalidate thinking about Gloria who's not חייב
חטאת chayav chatas right does not invalidate. All right. So we'll end
with that and we will continue tomorrow to go more directly to
this whole idea of לשמה lishma by קרבנות korbanot and where we
get that from.